- This is the world's largest 3D metal printer.
这是世界上最大的3D金属打印机
It was built by Relativity Space,
由Relativity Space公司打造
a startup that aims to print an entire rocket,
这家初创公司的目标是
including fuel tanks and rocket engines, in just 60 days.
在60天内，打印一支包括了燃料仓和发动机的火箭
I'm like looking inside a 3D printed rocket
我面前的就是一支3D打印的火箭
that is actually gonna go to space.
而且它真的能飞上太空
This giant hunk of metal, it's unbelievable.
这么一大块金属，真是难以置信
This video is sponsored by Omaze.
本视频由Omaze赞助
Offering you the chance to win a trip to space.
他能提供一个让你赢得太空之旅的机会
More about that at the end of the show.
详情请见视频结尾
- There's a lot of UV coming off the welds,
焊接点会有很强的紫外线
you can film it, but don't look directly at it.
拍摄没问题，但是不要用眼睛直接看
You get sunburned fast,
强紫外线会让人很快晒伤，
so it's like you're suiting up to go in a volcano.
所以我们全副武装，按照进火山的标准来
All right, we're gonna go in to the 3D printer,
好了，我们现在能进去看看
and see how it works.
3D打印机是怎么工作的
All right, so, yep, just hold this up.
好啦，可以，拿着这个
Don't look at it.
别直接看
We are in the printer.
我们进入了这里
- I can see it over there.
能看到打印机就在前面
- If we walk around here, we can get up close.
走这边能看得近一点
(machinery whirring)
(machinery beating)
So that's the wire melt team,
这个就是线材融化模组
and the print head moving around.
打印头在不断移动
So that's the plasma discharge, and it's hard to tell,
等离子体在放电，我不确定具体时长
but it's doing things every couple of milliseconds,
大约几毫秒放电一次
it's actually changing the electric wave form,
通过不断改变放电的波形
which is how it's controlling the deposition so well.
来来控制金属的精确沉积
- Do you know the temperature of it?
你知道这里的温度么？
Like, is it just above melt temp?
比方说，温度刚刚超过了熔点？
- It's just above melting for aluminum.
是的，比铝的熔点高一些
Yeah, probably a few hundred degrees above.
大概几百度吧
- The melting point of aluminum is 660 degrees Celsius.
铝的熔点约为660摄氏度
So the whole body of the rocket
所以，整个火箭的身体
is effectively melted together one tiny bit at a time.
都是一点点融化再凝固得来的
- All the raw metal
火箭所需所有的原材料就是这个
for the whole rocket that's printed is this.
It's a, you know, we kind of joke
我们都开玩笑
it's like Charlotte's web.
这就是“夏洛特的网”
Like a spider silk, but this is an aluminum alloy
就行蜘蛛丝一样，但这里是铝合金丝
that's on a wire spool.
绕线盘上都是
We actually print about 10 inches a second.
打印速度大约每秒10英寸（每秒25厘米）
So this wire is really going super fast,
这个线跑得飞快
and then the combination of lasers and plasma arc discharge
然后激光和等离子体放电共同作用
are working to melt both of them together at the same time.
把铝合金丝融化
- So where does the wire come out?
铝丝从哪儿出来？
- So it's right there, and then the electric arc discharge
这里，然后电弧在尖端处放电
happens right at the tip of the wire too.
- This is a camera.
- Yeah, that's a camera.
这是摄像头？对
- But why would you want to 3D print a rocket?
但是，为什么我们要3D打印火箭呢？
Is it just because we can?
就因为我们有这个能力？
It's funny to me that
听起来这很有趣
you had this experience with 3D printing where you're like,
你有3D打印的体验
oh, 3D printing is clearly the future.
然后说，啊，3D打印可是未来科技啊
Whereas, I feel like a lot of people's experience
然而，很多人和我一样，用3D打印的体验
with 3D printers as mine has been,
it's like incredibly frustrating.
都惨不忍睹
I feel like 3D printing is that thing
我感觉3D打印就是那种看起来不错
that seems like it should be great,
and yet whenever I try it,
一上手亲自做，总是得不到满意的效果
I don't get a result that I'm happy with.
- Yeah, I know.
是，我明白
I can tell you, we had plenty of experiences
我想说的是，在头几年，我们有很多（失败）的经验
the first couple of years,
where we ended up with a pile of metal and it didn't work.
打印出来一大堆东西，结果根本不能用
- But there are actually good reasons to 3D print a rocket.
不过用3D打印技术来生产火箭还是有很充足理由
A rocket has four major systems.
火箭由四个主要系统构成
Payload, guidance, structural, and propulsion.
载荷、制导、结构、推进
The bulk of the rocket is made up of the propulsion system,
火箭很大一部分都是推进系统
including the propellant tanks and the rocket engines.
包括了燃料仓和火箭发动机
Cryogenic fuel and oxidizer are pumped
燃料和助燃剂由燃料泵喷入燃烧室内
through an injector into the combustion chamber
where they react, releasing an enormous amount of heat.
反应燃烧后产生大量的热
This causes the exhaust gases to expand,
使得排出的气体迅速膨胀
exiting the rocket nozzle at high velocity.
以极高的速度排出发动机喷嘴
The faster this exit velocity
出口速度越快
and the higher the mass flow rate,
喷出工质的速率越高
the more thrust that can be generated.
火箭发动机产生的推力就越大
So rockets are huge, complex engineering projects,
因此，火箭是一项极为庞大，极为复杂的工程项目
which up to this point have largely been manufactured
同时，现阶段还是通过传统的手段来建造的
using traditional techniques.
That means before you can build the rocket,
也就是说，要想造一支火箭
you first have to build the tools to build the rocket.
你需要先制造出能够加工火箭的工具（类似船坞）
For example, to build NASA's next huge rocket,
比方说，为了制造NASA的下一支大火箭
the Space Launch System or SLS,
太空发射系统，简称SLS
they first needed to construct
他们先建造了垂直组装中心（VAC）
the vertical assembly center or VAC.
This is a 170 foot tall tool for welding together
这是个将170英尺（约51.8米）的大家伙
the domes, rings, and barrel sections
用于焊接燃料仓的仓顶，仓壁以及加强环
of the rocket's fuel tanks.
- They built that like an aerospace thing,
他们就像建造航天飞机那样
and they've had to spin up all these custom tooling designs
采用了大量的定制工具
and validate that those work
并在实际建造之前进行大量的验证工作
before actually starts
building the rocket.
并在实际建造之前进行大量的验证工作
And they finally got one being assembled on the pad
最终，花了11年才在发射台上组装好
after 11 years of development.
In contrast, Relativity Space the company,
相较而言，Relativity Space公司刚刚成立五年半
is just five and a half years old,
and they plan to launch their first rocket this year.
今年就准备发射他们的第一支火箭了
- I see this as a like old engineering style
在我看来，这就是传统模式和硅谷模式的区别
versus Silicon valley
style of build something,
在我看来，这就是传统模式和硅谷模式的区别
figure out what's wrong with it,
找出当前存在的问他
and build another thing that fixes those, right?
然后快速迭代，改进问题
The differences, I've always done that with software.
在软件领域，这种做法很常见
These guys are doing it with aerospace hardware.
但是这些人正在太空硬件领域实现它
- So this is the actual rocket tank structure
这个就是真正的火箭燃料仓
of what we're gonna be launching to orbit
今年年底发射的火箭就要用上了
at the end of this year.
So this actual thing is launching to space.
这是真正能上天的玩意儿
- That will go to space?
就是这个要上天？
- This will go to space,
就是它要上天
and it's by far the largest 3D printed product really,
目前为止，在世界上所有能飞的东西里，这是最大的3D打印部件
of any type ever made that's gonna fly.
I think maybe of any type in the world.
也许连不能飞的也算上，它也是最大的
- But it still looks 3D printed.
但是很明显这个还是3D打印的
Like you can still see the layers.
还是能看到一层层的
- Yeah, yeah, you can still see the layers.
对对，能看到一层层的
It only adds an extra 5 to 10% of the mass
这样的粗糙度，会增加5%到10%的重量
with the roughness.
When you actually cross section the material
当你检查材料的横断面时
and look at the machine parts of it,
it looks like normal metal.
与普通材料并无二致
Like actually at this end, this is printed as well.
尾部这里也是3D打印的
We just machine it afterwards.
我们后期又进行了加工
So it looks like normal metal in the joint sections.
连接处看起来和普通金属一样
- Does the surface roughness cause any aerodynamic problems?
这样粗糙的表面会影响气动性能么？
- No, none at all.
不会，完全不会
Yeah, it's actually the exact same aerodynamically.
空气动力性能完全一致
This whole thing, we simulate the print before printing,
整个构件在打印前进行了模拟打印
because if you just printed, you know, the 3D file
如果你直接把3D模型扔进去
and said press print, you would end up with a printer
按打印键的话，成品会受热扭曲
that's warped and like material falling all over the place
打印头无法把材料沉积上去，全都撒掉了
that wouldn't actually work.
火箭也没法用了
So we've invented software that reverse warps
所以我们的打印软件会自动抵消部件的扭曲
the whole part before printing it.
So the robots are actually doing this
机器人才能在扭曲后的部件上完成打印
really wobbly, weird shape,
but then it's actually perfectly straight
最终的成果非常精确
within a human hair at the entire length.
误差不会超过一根头发
- As it cools
- As it cools.
-当它冷却之后 -对，当它冷却后
The warpy thing turns into the...
扭曲的部件能够变成（笔直的火箭）
- And then we simulate all of that.
我们模拟了这些扭曲
So it's a big computational solver that simulates it,
模拟这些是个很大型的计算过程
and there's many, many other problems
同时还有很多很多其他的问题
we've had to solve to actually get
解决了这些问题
printing a rocket to work.
才能打印出能用的火箭来
But it's all these little pieces
而这也只是这些年中遇到问题的一部分
over the last couple of years,
and we've really started to hit some breakthroughs,
然后我们开始取得了一些突破性进展
which is also why now you see a whole rocket.
因此才能看到这里的一整个火箭
Yeah, you can step up here actually if you want.
你可以站上来
- Can I?
可以吗？
- Yeah, yeah.
可以
(man laughs)
哈哈哈哈哈哈
- Hello.
有人吗
I'm like looking inside a 3D printed rocket
这个3D打印的火箭之后可是要进入太空的
that is actually gonna go to space.
而我现在正在朝里面看
- Yes.
确实
- This giant hunk of metal.
这一大块金属
It's unbelievable.
真是让人难以置信
There's like rings inside.
这里面看起来有一圈一圈的圆环
- Those are printed in stiffeners.
那些是一体化打印的加强筋
And so those help prevent the rocket
防止火箭外壳扭曲变形
from buckling and crumpling.
So if you had a Coke can, and didn't pop the tab,
例如你有一个没开封的可乐罐
if you try to step on it, it's almost impossible
你用脚几乎不可能把它踩瘪
because there's pressure inside
因为罐内有气压让它保持坚挺
that keeps it from buckling.
But then when you pop the tab,
一旦你拉开拉环
there's no pressure and you can crunch it super easy.
里面压力和外部相同了，你很容易就能把罐子压瘪
It's not hard at all.
几乎不费吹灰之力
So rockets are the same.
火箭本体也是这样
The 50 PSI of pressure,
火箭内部有50磅每平方英寸（约3.4个标准大气压）的压强
which is about the same as a car tire,
跟汽车车轮内的压强差不多
keeps it inflated and keeps it from crumpling,
这个压强使火箭不至于变形或者瘪下去
but then the stiffeners also help keep it rigid.
加强筋的作用就是让它变得更牢固
- Yeah, so believe it or not,
还有一点就是
a rocket tank is thinner versus its diameter
如果用厚度和直径做比值的话，火箭燃料箱的相对厚度比可乐罐还要薄
than a Coke can.
So when you look at a Coke can,
你知道一个可乐罐有多大，以及它的侧壁有多薄吧
you know how big it is and then how thin it is,
a rocket tank is actually thinner than that.
按比例的话，火箭燃料箱比可乐罐还薄
So yeah, it's pretty light.
总之燃料箱是很轻的
It has to be very light.
它必须得做得轻才行
- Sure.
是啊
Aerospace companies started using metal 3D printing
航空技术公司早在10几年前就开始用3D打印技术打印一些复杂的小零部件了
over a decade ago to construct small complex parts.
For example, the injector.
比如说燃料喷射装置
- That is the most important part of any rocket engine,
这是火箭发动机上最重要的部件
where you basically gotta take the liquid propellant,
液体燃料在此处被雾化然后迅速混合
and turn it into a fine mist
that mixes really rapidly.
And those have actually been transitioned
现在在整个航空业中我们都使用3D打印来制造这个部件
to 3D printing all over the industry.
- Traditionally, something like this,
传统的燃料喷射装置
it's a bucket engine injector.
So it mixes liquid oxygen
把液氧和液体甲烷混合
and liquid methane propellants together,
and this is what actually produces all the fire and flame
这就是产生所有那些火光和火焰的地方
that is in a rocket engine.
这个就是所谓的火箭发动机
Traditionally, it would be over a thousand individual pieces
以前的话，需要用超过一千个零部件
and it would take nine months,
耗时9个月
but here we're 3D printing the whole thing in one piece.
现在我们用3D打印一气呵成
It takes two weeks and it costs 10 times less.
只需要2个星期，成本还只有原来的十分之一
- One of the big benefits of 3D printing
3D打印最大的好处之一就是
is reducing the number of parts.
可以减少零部件的数量
Have you ever thought about
你有没有想过火箭的燃烧室中有多高的温度？
how inside a rockets combustion
chamber, it gets really hot.
Up to 3,500 Kelvin.
温度可以高达3500开尔文
That's hot enough to melt virtually any metal.
这个温度可以熔化几乎任何金属
So how do the combustion chamber and rocket nozzle not melt?
那么燃烧室和火箭喷口为什么没熔化？
The answer is they're cooled by passing
因为外部环绕有低温推进剂给它们降温
the cryogenic propellants over them.
- On the Space Shuttle main engines.
在航天飞机的主引擎里
I love to talk about them because inside those engines,
这个话题我想想都激动
it's hot enough to boil iron.
引擎内部的温度足以让铁水沸腾
On the outside, you can freeze stuff
而引擎的外部还在结冰呢
to the exterior of this because you're running liquid
因为外部有循环流动的液氢
hydrogen through these things.
But to make those,
但是，为了达到冷却的效果
you basically had to take thousands of very small pipes,
需要做数千根极细的管子
and then you would form them
并且把管子做成符合燃烧室和喷嘴的形状
into the shape of the combustion chamber and the nozzle,
and then you would braze
weld them together.
然后再把它们钎焊到一起
And this was a ridiculously
labor-intensive task.
这无比的费时费力
You would have 1,080 individual
pipes running up the side,
因为总共有1080根管子
all having to be weld together
to make the combustion chamber and the nozzle
需要焊接在航天飞机引擎燃烧室和喷嘴的外壁
on the Space Shuttle engines.
So you can actually 3D print these things.
而其实这些完全可以3D打印出来
- This is a rocket nozzle being 3D printed,
现在正在3D打印的就是一个火箭喷嘴
and you can see the channels for the cryogenic propellants
你可以看到用来运输低温推进剂的管道
being printed right into the single part
是一体打印上去的
instead of having to add a thousand pipes on the outside.
而不需要再额外加上一千根管子
Smaller parts like these are typically 3D printed
通常像这样的小部件都是用金属粉末和激光3D打印而成的
using metal powder and lasers.
- So you can see the cooling channels
你看这些冷却管道是这样一体制作而成
are all being built as the one piece.
So this is a nozzle.
这是一个喷口
It really just lays down a layer of powder
打印机每次铺一层金属粉
that's about a 20th the thickness of a human hair.
厚度大概是头发的二十分之一
So it's really, really fine layers
就是很薄很薄的一层
just over and over and over and over relentlessly
但是不断地重复重复再重复
for probably about a week or so,
差不多一个星期
and then out comes the rocket nozzle
一个一体成形的火箭喷口就大功告成了
all printed as one piece.
It's way cheaper than traditional.
这比传统方法便宜多了
And this has four lasers going at once.
而且这个是四束激光同时工作
- That's amazing.
太赞了
- I get asked a lot, weren't 3D printed metals
经常有人问3D打印出来的金属会不会强度不够
not very strong?
Or how can it actually work?
甚至质疑这真的能行吗
But the printed materials are stronger
其实打印出来的材料比用传统方法制成的强度要更大
than they would be built
traditionally, actually.
It's counterintuitive.
这有点反直觉
- It is.
是啊
- Because we develop our own custom alloys in house.
我们使用的合金是自己研发的
So we have a whole material science team
我们有一个材料科学的团队专门负责研发3D打印所用的合金
just developing our own
alloys for 3D printing,
and the fact that it melts and then cools and solidifies
因为材料在极短的时间内从熔化到冷却到固化
very, very quickly, you can take advantage
我们可以利用这个物理原理
of that physics principle to get really strong alloys.
来得到强度很高的合金
- Another major benefit of 3D printing
3D打印带来的另一个好处是产品可以快速迭代
is that it allows for rapid iteration.
You can build a part quickly, test it,
部件建造起来很快，对它进行测试以后
and then redesign rapidly and print again.
又能很迅速地重新设计然后打印出来
- So this is a version of the engine
这个引擎是3年前的版本
that's about three
years old at this point,
but what's amazing is when you actually look
你再看看我们现在的引擎
at the engine design today,
it looks entirely different than this.
完全就不一样了
So each version we build, we can iterate and make better.
我们每个版本，都能快速迭代，愈发完善
So that's the other, you know,
这个就是所谓的
when we say software driven manufacturing,
「软件驱动型制造」
that's really what it is.
说的很有道理
Since you don't have fixed tooling,
因为不需要固定式加工设备
all the part geometries are just controlled
所有部件的几何学特性都由电脑辅助设计模型（CAD）所控制
via the CAD model, and then the printers just print
打印机只需要按照文件内容打印就行了
direct from file essentially.
It means you can actually change the design extremely fast.
因此想要更改设计就变得易如反掌
So building a whole engine only takes us about a month.
制造一个完整的引擎只需要花费差不多一个月
So then a month later, you can do a better version,
一个月以后，一个更好的版本就制造好了
and a month later, a better version than that.
如此迭代
So this particular one will actually be,
你现在看到的这个
I believe one of the first flight engines
应该是第一个在真实发射时会用到的引擎
that's actually launching to orbit on our first rocket.
- So this tubing, not 3D printed, right?
这些管道应该不是3D打印的吧？
- Not today.
现在还不是
- Okay.
确实
- In the future versions, we're actually integrating that
未来的话，我们正在把这些管道也整合进需要打印的部分
into the printed housings.
And we're gonna have a way that that's all printed too.
我们之后会想办法让这个变成纯3D打印的
- Perhaps the biggest impact
3D打印的使用
of the 3D printing approach could be to totally transform
最大的影响可能是会颠覆火箭的外形
what a rocket looks like.
With 3D printing, engineers can build parts
有了3D打印，可以制造出一些在传统方法看来不实际或是不可能的结构
that would be impractical or impossible
with traditional techniques.
Smooth, curvy, bio-inspired designs
光滑的，弯曲的，仿生的设计
are just as easy to print
as ordinary structures.
与普通结构同样易于打印
- This is actually part of our next rocket, Terran R.
这个是我们下一代火箭 「人族R」的一部分
So it's even larger.
还更大了哈
- This is like the base of a tank.
这个看起来像是燃料箱的底座
- Yeah. Yeah.
没错
So it's gonna go out.
它大概有...
It's almost done printing.
这几乎全是打印出来的
It's gonna go out about to here.
它大概向外能到这儿
So it's 16 foot diameter, but it's almost like a shell.
直径16英尺，外形像个贝壳
- I was gonna say like,
this reminds me of suddenly
啊我也想说，这个突然就让我以为
we're in The Little Mermaid or something.
我们身处在 小美人鱼 还是什么电影里面
- Yeah, yeah.
是啊是啊
Yeah, it's just for stiffness though.
这个外形主要是因为它稳固
- It's not that you plan to make it bio inspired.
不是说我们故意想把它造成仿生的
It's like that structure is actually the optimal structure.
而是这个结构就是最优结构
- Yeah, yeah.
嗯对
- We're actually designing many features in the rocket
这个火箭的设计里
that could not be manufactured
unless it was 3D printed,
有好多都是只能用3D打印完成的
which is one of the secret sauces
这也是为什么我们要开一家公司来对付这些秘密配方
of why you had to build a
whole company around it,
is because our rocket actually looks
我们3D打印出来的火箭与传统火箭将会是截然不同的
entirely different 3D printed than it does traditionally.
Like in my mind, it's been more akin
我觉得用内燃机向电动机的转变类比比较合适
to like gas internal
combustion engine to electric.
You know, really, people are trying to put batteries
一直以来汽车厂商都想在现有的汽车里装上电池和电动机
and electric motors into
existing products for decades.
Like everyone knew electric vehicles were the future,
因为大家都知道电动汽车才是未来趋势
but Nissan and Ford had really not compelling products
而日产和福特很长一段时间都没什么让人种草的产品了
for a long time.
It wasn't until a company came along called Tesla
直到有个叫特斯拉的公司反应过来
that decided, well, actually
the shift to electrification
啊，朝着电气化的转变
means the batteries, the electric motors, the factory,
意味着电池、电动机、工厂
the design of the product,
产品设计
how we're actually gonna scale the company,
公司规模
the supply chain, all of it's different
供给链这一系列的转变
because of electrification.
I mean, that's in some ways,
从某种程度上说
the dirty secret of electric cars
总体零件少了很多
and why they're able to be automated in production
就是电动车成功，以及能快速生产的「肮脏秘密」
because the part count is so much lower.
So for a fully 3D printed rocket,
对于3D打印的火箭
we have a hundred times fewer parts,
我们要达到的目标就是只使用百分之一的零件数量
which is what we're guiding to.
There's no fixed tooling in our factory at all.
在我们工厂里不存在固定式加工设备
Unlike the rest of aerospace
反观其他航空制造企业
that's still really, 60 years later,
还在用60年前阿波罗时代的方法
even since Apollo. Building products
one at a time by hand with hundreds of thousands
手工打造成千上万个零部件
to millions of individual parts.
And no one's really changed that paradigm
这种航空制造的模式还没人打破呢
of how an aerospace factory actually fundamentally works.
- Yeah, this is the new fully 3D printed rocket.
这就是完全3D打印的新火箭
So yeah, we'll have dragonfly wing type structures
嗯，我们会仿造蜻蜓翅膀的结构设计格栅翼
and we're building it so.
我们已经开始制造了
But that's the first one,
不过，左边那台才是初号机
and then that's that one for scale.
那台是尺寸更大的版本
So yeah, it is definitely bigger.
嗯，绝对大了一圈
Yeah, so our rocket is named
Terran One and Terran R,
是的，我们把火箭命名为 「人族一号」 和 「人族R」
and then our 3D printer's Stargate.
3D打印机则被称为 「星际之门」
So all the things here at Relativity
Relativity 制造的所有产品
are named after StarCraft.
名字都来源于 「星际争霸」 这款游戏
So yeah, of course, the Stargate printer
啊哈，「星际之门」
was with the Protoss
used to warp in spaceships.
本来是「神族」乘坐太空飞船时扭曲空间所用的工具
And so, that's what's warping
in spaceships at Relativity.
所以，那就是 Relativity 用来改变太空飞船的利器
We have a system in our
avionics called the Pylon
我们的产品中，有一套名为「水晶塔」的系统
that we have to build a lot of.
这套系统我们需求量很大
So we always joke, we have to
construct additional Pylons.
所以我们经常开玩笑说，我们还得多造一点「水晶塔」啊
Most people don't know how rockets
很多人对于传统的火箭制造方式
are built traditionally at all anyway.
也所知甚少
And I think a lot of
people assume it's rockets,
我觉得，许多人以为这是火箭
so shouldn't it be already very advanced
那它就应该已经非常先进了
and robots everywhere and you know,
生产线上全是机器人，你知道的
Elon's got Space X and Tesla,
马斯克有SpaceX和Tesla两家公司
so doesn't Space X just look like Tesla
那SpaceX难道不像Tesla那样
with all these robots and automation?
同样有这些机器人和自动化的设备
But that's really not true.
但这大错特错了
I mean, aerospace hasn't
adopted automation at all.
我想说的是，航空工业并没有完全接纳自动化
- One of the issues, right,
is that you're not making
其中一个问题就是，恩，你总不会一次性制造
a lot of rockets?
很多的火箭吧？
- Right?
对吧？
- So there's no incentive
to like figure out
所以并没有那么大的需求去刺激他们
how to tool up a factory
to like pump out rockets
设计出一种自动化的工厂，用来大量生产火箭
like a hundred a day or something.
比如每天生产一百枚的那种
- Exactly.
是这样
- Like you would for cars.
就像生产汽车那样
- Exactly, you're not making a lot.
的确，你并不会造那么多
Even with commercial aircraft,
即使是商用的飞机
you're not making nearly as many
也完全达不到那么多的产量
and there's orders of magnitude
more parts and complexity.
另外航空器的零部件数量和复杂程度与其他相比是差了数量级的
A commercial aircraft has
several million individual parts.
一架商用飞机有数以百万计独立的零件
So to have robots assemble
several million parts
让机器人组装数百万个零件
when an automobile has tens of thousands
和仅有数万零件的汽车相比
is completely different.
是完全不同的
It's a much harder problem.
这个问题难多了
So that's where 3D printing
is automation for aerospace
所以，在我们这里，3D打印实现了航空业的自动化
because you're not assembling
all those parts with robots
因为你并不是像装配汽车那样
like you would with a car,
用机器人组装所有的组件
you're assembling them in the 3D file
你是预先在3D文件里设计整合好它们
and then the printer just
prints them assembled.
然后打印机以组装好的状态打印出它们
- The plan for Relativity Space,
Relativity Space 的计划
is it low-earth orbit or is
it going further than that?
是专注于近地轨道，还是会有更远的目标？
- So for Terran One, it's
mostly low earth orbit.
对于「人族一号」而言，主要是近地轨道
The first rocket.
这是我们的第一款火箭
Terran R can actually send
payload to the moon to Mars.
而「人族R」实际上可以把载荷送往月球和火星
I mean, it's pretty, pretty huge.
它的运力相当巨大
I founded the company
because I really thought
我创立这家公司，因为我真心觉得
that there needed to be, you know,
你明白的，需要有
dozens of hundreds of
companies making Mars happen.
数以千计的公司一起努力，使得前往火星成为现实
We're focused on taking
this 3D printing tech
我们专注于这种3D打印科技
and what we call the
factory of the future,
还有被我们称为未来工厂的概念
and one day shrinking it down to something
在未来的某一天将它压缩成
we'll actually launch to Mars
and build an industrial base.
我们能够真正发射到火星的小工厂
并且建起一个工业基地
So that's the long-term
vision of the company,
那是我们公司的长期愿景
is build the industrial base on Mars.
就是在火星建立这种工业基地
In many ways, this factory
is just a prototype.
在许多方面，这种工厂还只是一个原型
It's still far smaller
than a traditional factory.
它仍然远小于传统的工厂
It's far lighter.
它的分量小得多
And I think it's inevitable
但是不可避免总有人要创建这样的公司
someone has to build this company.
- I don't know that in 10, 20 years
我不知道，在十年，或者二十年后
that you will be 3D printing
rockets all the time.
你会不会随时能乘坐3D打印的火箭
Because if you are flying lots of rockets,
因为如果有大量的火箭投入运营
it becomes cheaper to have
a dedicated machine for it.
拥有这样一个火箭的花费会更少
I do think that as a
company, they are well-placed
我认为，作为一家公司，他们的定位相当重要
because even if Terran fails
to capitalize on the market,
因为即使「人族」系列没能在市场上发挥优势
even if nobody wants to
use it as a launch vehicle,
即使没人愿意用它作为发射载具
they are clearly now the world experts
我们显然是目前世界级的
on 3D printing rocket hardware,
3D打印火箭硬件专家
'cause they've done everything, right?
因为他们把所有问题都解决了，不是吗
They've tried to apply
3D printing to places
他们努力将3D打印应用在
where a lot of people dismissed it.
被许多人忽视的领域
So I think they're sort
of secure as a company.
所以我觉得他们作为一家公司，地位是相当稳固的
Whether we will see rockets
being 3D printed all the time?
我们会不会看到火箭完全由3D打印制造的那天呢
That's a good question.
这是个好问题
- There've been a lot of talk recently
最近有许多的讨论
about billionaires going to space.
有关于前往太空的大富豪们
- Yeah.
是的
- Will a 3D printed
rocket make it possible
3D打印的火箭会使前往太空变得可行
and a lot cheaper for me to go to space?
并且为我节省一大笔钱吗
- Yes, I mean, certainly what we're doing
是的，我想说的是，很明显我们在做的
is lowering the cost.
正是降低费用
So our rockets are
costing about five times
所以说，我们的火箭花费会比当今的可回收火箭便宜五倍
to, you know, I believe we can get to 10
到，emm，我觉得我们可以达到十倍
or even a hundred times cheaper
甚至能达到一百倍
with a fully reusable rocket
than what we have today.
So it can definitely
climb down the cost curve.
那么这绝对能压低成本曲线
But I also think, you know, going to Mars
不过，我还觉得，emm，前往火星
and the first people that are going,
还有最先到达那里的人
it really is about what is the
point of being a human being?
重要的是成为人类的意义是什么
Like for me, why go to Mars?
比方说，对我而言，为什么要去火星？
If we were having this conversation
假如我们正在谈这个话题
and a million people were
living on another planet,
而一百万人住在另一个星球
I think it would expand the possibilities
我想，这将带来更多可能性
of human experience and what
it means to be a person.
人类的体验和生而为人的意义
Like we'd have YouTube channels on Mars
就像，我们可以开个关于火星的频道
and people sharing what life
on Mars is like versus earth.
人们可以分享在火星的生活是怎样的，并且和地球比较
And there'd be long distance
Amelie, like love stories.
还会有异地版的「天使艾美丽」，爱情故事之类的
Like I think there's
just a lot of richness
就像我觉得，人类有很多可能性
in what human culture
and society can be about.
文化和社会的演进令人期待
Yes, I think there's criticism about,
当然，我想会有一些批评，关于，
you know, billionaires going to space
你懂的，大富豪上太空之类的
and I don't agree with.
对这些声音我不敢苟同
You know, all of the projects
你明白的，所有这些计划
need to actually add up to
some vision that is meaningful.
都需要被赋予一个有意义的愿景
I think that's really important.
我觉得那真的很重要
But I do think going to
Mars is really just about,
但我不觉得去火星仅仅是为了
you know, we've lived
for generations on earth,
emm，我们世世代代生活在地球上
so what's it all about like,
那，去火星是怎样的感觉？
why do we want to keep
improving and getting better
我们为什么想要改进
and furthering society on earth?
并且拓展地球上的社会
So for me, it's pretty existential.
对我而言，这是相当存在主义的问题
What it means to be a human being.
成为人类意味着什么呢
(techy sound effect)
- Hey, this video is sponsored by Omaze.
嘿，这个视频由 Omaze 赞助
Offering you the chance
to win a trip to space.
这个金主现在给你个机会去太空兜风
The winner will get two seats
on one of Virgin Galactic's
中奖的幸运儿能拿到两张维珍银河的船票
first commercial space flights.
这可是维珍银河的第一次商业飞行哦
Meaning you and a guest
will travel 80 kilometers
你可以再带一个人上天，飞到80千米那么高
up in the sky.
You'll get to see the
curve of planet earth,
到时候你可以看到地球的曲线
experience weightlessness,
体验失重感
and become one of the
few people in the world
成为地球上少有的那一群
to have gone to space.
前往过太空的人类
And you also get to
join Sir Richard Branson
你还可以和理查德布兰森爵士一起
for a personal VIP tour
of Spaceport America.
体验美国太空港的VIP旅行
The flight is estimated to
take place in early 2022.
这个飞行预计排定在2022年上半年
So enter at omaze.com/veritasium
for your chance to win.
那猛戳这个链接试试手气吧
Now, Omaze partners with charities,
Omaze 和慈善机构一起
in this case Space for Humanity,
这一次是和 Space for Humanity 合作
an organization whose mission
is to expand access to space
这是个以扩大前往太空途径为己任的组织
and train global leaders
in the eventual goal
并培养全球领导者为他们的终极目标服务
of creating a sustainable future.
创造一个可持续的未来
So part of your contribution
supports this cause.
那么，你的一小部分贡献将支持这一事业
To potentially win a trip to space
想薅太空船票
and support Space for
Humanity, a great cause,
并且支持这个组织的伟大事业吗
go to omaze.com/veritasium.
猛击这个链接
I will put that link
down in the description.
我会把这个链接放在视频描述里
So I wanna thank Omaze
for sponsoring this video,
最后在此感谢 Omaze 赞助这期视频
and I wanna thank you for watching.
也谢谢你的观看